[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host PESA manut today our
guest is Andreas Muller Andreas is a
co-founder of toddle a no code tool for
building scalable performance web
applications he's an experienced vice
president of engineering with a
demonstrated history of working in the
information technology and services
industry Andreas welcome to the show
thank you very much and thank you for
having me so today we going to talk
about no code platforms let's jump and
get started with the basics Andreas can
you help our listeners by defining what
is new code yes so that's a really good
question because I think there are quite
a lot of different definitions floating
around
but the general definition we go by and
and and I think is largely also the most
broad one is it's any kind of Technology
where traditionally that's been solved
by writing code but they are now a
different approach so I mean like a
visual way of doing it and so maybe the
most famous example of this and I think
also the tool that coin the term is web
flow which is an application for
building websites and there's quite a
lot of it's been a very popular space
for a couple of years now for the last
at least five years we've seen a lot of
new tools come out so it's very much a
growing space and we're seeing more and
more of these platforms pop up and even
last year we saw several quite prominent
platform launch right and I also know
that the term low code is used quite
frequently are no Code and low code the
same I think that there's sort of a a
minor difference in the terms they are
very often used interchangeably so there
is not a clear distinction that you can
always rely on but I think the term low
code is largely the idea that entirely
removing code from a normal workflow is
either not possible or not easily
achieved and as a result you sort of end
up with a little bit of a mix and mat
solution where you'll add some code here
and there but a lot of the things you're
building you're still building without
code so I think the main difference is
that with low code you are still coding
as part of your daily workflow and in no
code workflow you might occasionally
have to add a little bit of code but
it's mostly done without writing any
code so it's just drag and drop and that
reduces the flexibility well so in a lot
of times in a lot of cases it can reduce
flexibility I mean you can overall say
it does but the way we generally see it
at least in total is that we are
limiting the number of ways you can do
something but we're not really limiting
what you can do and so the limitations
of each tool is very is dependent on the
tool some tools are very optimized for
Speed and ease of use and in return they
also limit a lot what you can actually
do with them others are a lot more Broad
and impose very little limitation on
what you can build while researching for
the session I came across an interesting
stats I'm just going to read it out
according to research and markets the
low code and no code development
platform Market is expected to generate
about 187 billion by 2030 and it was
about 30 billion in 2023 Gartner also
estimates that 70% of new applications
are going to be developed in Enterprises
by using no code or low code
Technologies by 225 up from less than
25% in 2020 and those numbers are just
mind-bogglingly huge what is fueling
this growth or adoption of no code so I
think the first thing to note with that
is that that's not that recent of a
study anymore and I would actually
suspect they might be even more bullish
if they had to do the same today mhm
because we have seen a lot of adoption
and we've also seen a lot of growth in
the number of tools out there I think
there's a few things fueling this and to
sort of understand a little bit about
that you also have to understand that
when we say no code tools or the no code
Market which like Gardner likes to say
there isn't really a no code Market
there's quite a lot of markets that has
no code tools in the definition I sort
of presented earlier saying it's it's
largely just a term that means an area
where everything used used to rely on
code where we now have a set of more
visual tools right but that really
doesn't Define a market very much so it
really does depend on the specific tool
you're talking about but the majority of
the no code sort of change has happened
in the area of where it enables
non-developers people who wasn't
traditionally developers to build
applications and we especially seeing a
large growth for internal software so
tools like retool jet admin has had
immense success with enabling companies
to build smaller internal tools very
easily and usually without actually
involving large part of the respective
engineering organizations so a lot of
times it's a way to sort of be able to
actually produce software but without
spending valuable time from your often
more highly paid employees in your
engineering department that's
interesting and leads us nicely into the
next topic of discussion which I wanted
to touch on which is what's the role of
developer in the no code Marketplace or
environment so according to you what's
the primary role of a developer in a no
code environment so I think for a lot of
cases for a lot of tools are really
designed for people who can't
traditionally code so they're really
designed with the first and foremost
principle of how simple can we make this
to a point where even if you never
programmed before you can fairly quickly
pick that up but at the other end of
that spectrum of no code which is where
total the company I I founded lies we're
a lot more focused on how can we improve
the efficiency of Technology teams so I
think there's one end where you
basically say we don't really need
programmers because we simplified things
so much that that knowledge isn't that
important anymore and in the other end
we have still professional software
teams and in our end in total and what
we're building developers are very much
uh big part of that while we're removing
a lot of the early frictions of learning
to code I think all your listeners will
know that's not all software Engineers
do there's actually quite a lot to the
job and you don't even code all of the
day right so there's still every bit as
much need for engineering we're still
building distributed system at the end
of the day and they have raised
conditions and problems and everything
we always run into you still need to do
data modeling and architecture and all
these things none of that went away the
only thing that we've slightly changed
is the fact that you don't need to spend
often several years learning a
programming language before you can get
started can you expand on that are there
any examples of tasks or
responsibilities that developers
typically handle in a no code project
yeah absolutely so I can sort of mostly
speak about how we do it at total so we
both build a no code tool the platform
but we are also working in it so since
totle is itself buildin total we build a
NOCO tool in itself so that that means
we are also a full company working every
day in this NOCO tool building it and
we're a cross functional team that
consists of Engineers designer as well
as a marketer we're fairly small team
still and the whole team including our
marketer actually works in total not
always daily obviously our marketer
there's a lot of other things but he's
also able to go in and make changes and
so what really changes in our setup is
that rather that having a more
traditional sort of almost assembly line
of features where you know a product
manager will come along and say let's
build this thing a designer will then
design it and engineer implements it
we're actually able to work in parallel
so Engineers can work on the logic of
one feature while the designer works on
the UI and they're not handing off the
design to be implemented they're
literally implementing the final UI so
by having that sort of dynamic I having
the like the role of the developer
didn't change but a lot of the sort of
more maybe cumbersome task of just
producing UI that someone already
designed that actually goes away and you
can start focus on the functionality in
the interaction which is I think what
most Engineers find to be more
interesting especially when building the
front end part of applications we will
Deep dive into the total development
model in terms of that platform itself
in the next section but before we go
there I had a few more questions on the
role of Developers the next one would be
do you have any examples of success
stories where developers have played a
crucial role in driving Innovation
through new Cod
development yeah I mean again I I think
our own case is a very good example of
building something immensely complex in
a no code setup right we've also had a
lot of examples among our customers we
had a person who signed up to totle and
actually managed to start a company in
10 days like from his start building an
app till you had it first customer and
bought it it took 10 days right and he
was a developer but he was not a
particularly experience developer he's
done some coding before but didn't have
a long career behind him right and we
also seeing examples of people switching
from like we have a few users that have
longer careers in coding that switch to
no code for the simple reason of you can
just deliver faster right you can
produce applications faster than you can
do in a traditional setup right and that
iteration time that sort of ability to
move fast ends up being incredibly
valuable agreed when I started coding we
had something called R rapid application
development and no code reminds me a lot
about that yeah I think there's a lot of
similarities I think forever we've been
chasing this idea of a lower feedback
time right most of my career has been as
a web developer and we sort of went from
in the old days where you wrote some
code and then uploaded it somewhere and
then had to refresh your browser to see
if it worked and then we started getting
build system and eventually we got some
Auto reload where the browser would
automatically refresh and it was the
greatest innovation in the world because
now it only took like two seconds from
you made a change to you could or maybe
five seconds because our page didn't
load so fast at the time and so we've
seen these improvements all the time and
the fact that feedback time has always
been a key metric to chase because we
know the lower the feedback time
essentially the faster you can
experiment and the faster you can
iterate right and what we're seeing with
no code especially for front end and for
building UI is that we're now getting
that feedback down to milliseconds so
you're really like clicking on something
you're selecting you're changing
properties and you're seeing the changes
right there you don't even have to look
away from what you're working on while
you're editing right so by getting that
cycle time down productivity just goes
way up and that keeps happening all the
way down to like when you're getting
down to a couple of milliseconds
feedback I also believe there's change
in perspective that needs to happen when
you start building out in no code
platforms so have you seen developers
facing challenges when they start out in
this new model of
development yeah I think one of the
things way to look at a no code platform
is you can kind of see it as a framework
that's very opinionated right because
generally no code platforms are so where
for example if if people work with web
development where something like react
is generally considered is very not
opinionated you can bring in whatever
other technology you're looking for
right however you want to do styling do
it that way however you want to do
routing and serice side rendering do it
that way I think we're looking at
something that's more on the end of like
Ruby on Rails where like there's one way
we do things and this is how you should
do it and if you don't do it that way
it's going to be harder right and no
code is like even more opinionative with
that so I think there's a lot of times
where you kind of have to say well
whatever platform you choose they made
some calls up front of this is how we
like doing and generally you need to
lean into that so totle for example
gives you a ton of flexibility on what
you can do but we generally have a
fairly strong opinion about how do you
do styling how do you do abnc so I think
that's usually the first one and we see
a lot of people like oh I wanted to do
it this way and we basically say well
you can achieve what you're looking for
but you can't do it that way right what
advice would you give developers who are
interested in exploring or transitioning
into the world of no code develop
well I think the first thing is it's
important to start out with an open mind
especially because I think a lot of if
it's a more experienced developer that's
been around for a time I think a lot of
them are sitting with the feeling of
we've heard this story before there is
nothing original the idea of no code or
visual development the earliest example
I've been able to find is from
1963 before it became a standard to have
monitors attached to computers someone
started to paint and start PR
programming with a light pen so it
really isn't new right and we've seen
all these examples of visual Basics was
probably one of the most successful ones
but we've also seen dream reav we see a
lot of them and they never really took
off and I think a lot of people have a
general feeling of it's nice and it's
cool but obviously you can't do real
programming with it right you can't
build anything complex that's the big
change that's happening today that we're
beginning to see platforms that actually
lets you build things that are immensely
complex things that are are scalable
beyond what most people ever thought was
possible with that so I think that's
probably the main thing come at it with
a little bit of an open mind because a
lot has happened since maybe last time
people took a step at this right yeah I
agreed I think it's important to
understand there is a lot of engineering
gone behind developing the noo platform
which allows you to move faster and not
treat it as something which is just for
fun in games absolutely the other thing
I wanted to touch on was methodology so
when you're developing software you
usually have the traditional way of
developing software is waterfall and now
mostly it's agile when you're doing no
code development what methodology do you
use well I think that kind of still is
left up to people I mean generally uh
your platform is not going to dictate
your team structure and they're not
going to dictate how you want to run
your software process I think the one
thing we've seen that's interesting is
that it opens up for a new way at at
least what we've experienced with tottle
it opens up for a new level of agility
that you didn't have before so as I said
like traditionally even if you're
working in agile what you're doing is
you're reducing your iteration time to
maybe your what you're spitting out in a
week but you're still having a team
that's put together people with
different backgrounds and you still
largely have this sort of designer
feeding designs to developer to be
implemented right and so what we've seen
a lot is that when you start bringing
iteration time down and not just
iteration time but also the time it
takes to actually go from I want to
start working on a feature till that
feature is done like the time to deploy
in total for example is incredibly short
as well so we've had cases where for
example a user has reported a bug and I
think our current record is 11 seconds
from it was reported Till There was a
fixed live now that was a really trivial
bug of course right but that's kind of
the level and when those tools become
available when you start changing what
the normal is all of a sudden your team
at least in our case also start working
a little bit different right so I've
worked in companies that had very large
complex set up for how you release a
feature where you have staging
environments and you have even
pre-staging environments and staging
environments and then you have level one
two and three environments before things
got released right and anything from
that to a way more sort of continuous
deployment model and with tottle we've
sort of been able to take that even
further where we are sort of internally
very heavily r on using feature Flags so
someone can literally push like we're
pushing to production I think we have a
five person team and we have days where
we push to production 20 to 30 times and
we are not always shipping all those
features a lot of times they're feature
flag so we're the only ones that
actually get to explore them but the
fact that we can do that and it's not
just Engineers that are doing that but
our designer is doing that as well right
he's modif design and actually get these
things out really really quickly so I
think that started sort of there's new
opportunities of how you can work which
is sort of like agile but even more
agile if you will the other question
I've got us you know something related
to my personal experience quite early on
in my career I worked as a VB6 developer
and VB6 had a very low barrier of Entry
almost anybody could pick it up and
start coding in VB6 and start delivering
to the business and that meant there
were a plethora of b six developers and
that Talent was easily available which
meant that the only way you could
differentiate was being very good in the
domain so you became a VB6 developer
with FX options knowledge which allowed
you to differentiate yourself in the job
market is it something similar for a
developer who is developing in a no code
platform and how do they progress in
their career I don't know if we've
entirely seen that Trend yet or at least
seen enough of it to conclude that's
where things are going but I think it's
a very likely outcome we've lowered the
barrier of Entry to development which
means that obviously a lot more people
can and I think one of the interesting
thing is as we saying all of a sudden
the designers on the total team are not
just designing anymore they are actually
developing but they're just developing a
very specific aspect of our application
so they are essentially uiux developers
and not just designers right they've
embraced that and without having to
fundamentally change that much about
their current skill set they've now
adopted a whole new role and at the same
time we're seeing a lot of our
developers that come from a traditional
coding background are are still doing
many of the same things they're doing
but a lot of the UI implementation work
they're not doing as much of anymore and
a lot of the traditional like there was
always a ton of tickets was like can you
please change the text on this button
that kind of stuff right which was never
really it didn't feel like there was a
reason to have a senior engineer handle
that one right so those kind of tasks
kind of go away because they're so easy
to implement for anyone that it's kind
of easier to fix it in the app than it
is to create a j ticket right yeah so I
think roles do change and I think to
some degree we are seeing more
specialization in that way towards focus
of design and focus on either logic or I
think we'll also see a lot more full
stack developers in this world because
if you understand the logic of how it
works one place and the other there's
not that big of a gap right kind of like
we saw it with JavaScript that once
people could start working in one
language all of a sudden we saw a lot
more full stack developers right what is
full stack in a no code world so I think
it larly means the same as it does in
the traditional sense so for example
tottle as as we build is only focused on
the front end so it's built to connect
to a back end whether that backend is
built in code or whether it's built in
in another no code tool that focuses on
the back end right but I think it
largely has the same responsibility of
someone that cuts across that network
connection between the browser and the
back end that focus on not just how do
we present this information to the user
and how do they interact with it but
also how do we store it how do we update
these things and it'll most likely be
anything from database design to
implementing a lot of this in the front
end as well so if anything it might go a
little bit further than it did before
okay and I think that's a good segment
to a next section which is a deep dive
into toddle and the question I've got to
start it off would be why does toddle
not have a database yes so there's a
couple of reasons actually why it
doesn't have a database one of them is
that it's practical not to have one so
when I started out looking at totle I
was sort of saying like how can I
actually make this work right I wanted
to build a tool where at least coding is
optional and it's very clear like if
coding is optional then where do you put
your source code doesn't make any sense
right right if I'm removing code as a
barrier to getting started you kind of
also have to remove your source code
GitHub style hosting right because it
doesn't really make sense to have that
so I also needed like a version control
system built for total like going line
by line and comparing anything wouldn't
make sense when you weren't working with
source code right and of course the last
part is actually figuring out how to
deploy all this and run it is also
something we often as Engineers end up
spending enormous amount of time on even
if we're using a service provider
there's still always work setting that
up so it's also very clear for this
access to work I would also need to have
a hosted service so I it's like I'm
building a programming language and
Editor to work with that program
language as well as a version control
system and a hosting provider I don't
really need to add more to that stack I
feel like that's already more than
enough to try and get working right so a
purely practical of saying trying to do
everything will mean that I'm gonna end
up doing most of it sort of less than
ideal right
but the other part is actually probably
for the same reason where we never
really saw a full stack code framework
we've seen some examples trying and then
I mean certainly some of them has been
more successful than others but the
model never won out and I think the
fundamental reason for that is that
while the front end tends to not be too
dependent on the kind of app You're
Building like whether you're building a
web shop or a social media platform or a
inter prise what a scheduling software
react tends to be the number one choice
of framework for the front end or there
are the choices and and I mean this is
certainly not a react is necessarily
better than any of them but it is the
most popular right so we have this one
framework that works across all of them
and the other Frameworks are not more
industry specific right they're all
super cross functional in nature now
when we go to the back end people start
to pick technology a little bit more
specifically based on a use case in the
front end we tend to largely just go
with the front end framework and you'll
pick one or the other but it's always
got to be one of the big three right on
the back end I think there's a lot more
variation so sometimes it makes sense to
have some lambdas running some
JavaScript sometimes you're setting up
go and Docker containers sometimes you
have you know magenda e-commerce
platform sometimes you're hooking into a
whole different system so I think when
you fundamentally look at frontend
Technologies stacks and backend
technology stack across different
companies you'll see a lot bigger
difference on the backend it'll be
easier to check what is this company
doing by looking at their back end as
opposed to the front end and I think
that's Lely why we haven't seen these
full stack Frameworks because the one
siiz fits all doesn't really exists at
least that's my theory to why that never
went out right I think you know Version
Control is one thing which is missing
from a majority of the no Cod platforms
available in the market and totally fill
step G were there other reasons why you
felt the need to build a new no code
platform yeah absolutely so I kind of
came at this from my own slight personal
use case so when I started considering
total I actually spent almost a year
trying to convince myself not to do it
because it's obviously a massive
undertaking to try and build something
like this but when I started looking at
like playing around with the idea of of
this got to be possible why does this
not exists can I figure out how to make
this obviously I looked into what
actually does that exist and obviously
the first thing I saw was like okay no
code is a is a very broad spectrum of a
lot of different solutions and we have
anything from like page Builders like
Squarespace right which is a no code
tool but it's very much not one for
building SAS applications and then as I
looked at the ones that were more
focused on building applications rather
than website that's a bit of a gray area
of overlap but I think in the more
complex end there was a few things I was
always missing so one of them as you
mentioned is Version Control which is I
don't think any engineer out there would
take a job if they said by the way we
don't use git we all work on the same
files and we just try not to ruin
everything I think nobody would really
want to work in that setup right and I
mean if you're one person it's fine if
you're two people it's very difficult
and if you're three people well you're
not all working at the same time so that
just from the world I was coming from of
more professional software engineering
of working with anything from startups
to Enterprise level companies the idea
of not having Version Control and like a
git style Version Control was just kind
of unheard of right like it wouldn't
make any sense so that was one of them
that was really key the other thing that
I had was performance is one of those
things that you don't care about until
you need it I think we had this
conversation the react Community a lot
is react fast is it fast enough I think
for many things it's fast enough but
it's definitely not fast and eventually
you might run into a scenario where it's
not fast enough and then you need to
consider something else right and that's
kind of the same with a lot of this in
in the no code world that's just the
same problem but at significantly lower
performance right and as I mentioned you
can often do a lot of things but how you
do them is differently so when you're
locked into a no code platform it
basically sets The Benchmark like it
sets the bar for how performant an
application can be it's not going to be
ever faster than the platform allows you
and fundamentally you have no ability to
influence that so just like with
Frameworks it is very important
Frameworks are fast because if you need
it to be fast there's nothing you can do
with people building the frame hasn't
build it that way it's the same thing
with no code and so that was a
limitation where I could see but I can't
invest in that as for a larger project
if this is the Baseline for performance
MH and I think the third bit was
basically basically I need to be able to
know that if I start building a project
in this like obviously in the
professional engineering world if we
make a bet on a technology you got to
also know that that holds six months
down the line or a year right and
obviously any new technology there's a
certain like you may not like what you
chose sometimes you make a choice and
you realize it wasn't the best choice
but it should never be in a situation
where the platform tells you this is not
possible Right it can't be the platform
dictating what kind of features you can
build and that was kind of the case for
all of the existing platforms like a lot
was possible but there's always a
limitations there was always a point
where it says you can get to here but
you can't get further and from where I'm
coming from those were sort of the basic
principle of saying we can't ever have
any of those right we got to have good
version control we've got to have really
good Baseline performance and we got to
have a platform that's flexible enough
so no matter what problem you end up
having there has to be a solution right
I'm very curious understanding how did
you solve the performance problem
because fundamentally a no code platform
allows you to build only within the
constraints of the platform so how do
you solve for it the interesting thing
is that that's actually a plus for
performance and not a negative right so
when you're building a framework or a
platform the more constrainted your
users are the easier it is to optimize
performance because the less edge cases
you have to deal with so in total it
kind of works I mean fundamentally total
works the same way as a web app built in
a framework it's a very like if you're
familiar with react angular view
actually any of those you'll really see
the influence and the parallels very
clearly when you start working with
todle and so we actually have the
additional benefit of because we're
building the language like the
underlying language as well as the
editor and the framework and the hosting
platform we can optimize things across
all three that would be very difficult
to do in a code setup so actually the
fact that there are some constraints in
how you can do things in total allows us
to optimize performance more than would
otherwise be possible now that doesn't
necessarily mean we're faster than every
web FR like some of the new Frameworks
out there like solid and quick are
showing really impressive performance
but I do think it means that we can be I
do think there's the possibility to
optimize total so down the line as we
invest more and more time in this I
think that the possibility to actually
Baseline be faster than most code
Frameworks for this very reason and how
do you balance that performance with the
flexibility you're able to provide your
users so that's a really good question
and I think it's not so much oneto one
that when we give more flexibility you
get less performance it's more when we
give more flexibility we give people the
opportunity to worsen the performance
right so there's always is a certain
level of like is this the responsibility
of the platform or is this the
responsibility of the developer right
and of course we could get really good
performance by just saying well it's
their responsibility we put it on the
the final developer right and then you
know if images are not optimized if
you're loading too much code or being
inefficient well you should not do so
much but I think our approach has sort
of been it there has to be a balance we
want to do as much as we can let's we
say flexibility is one of our core
principles we never want to not allow
you to do something we just want to make
sure that you're doing it in the
smartest way possible so we don't strike
so much a Balon there like we rarely
ever limit your flexibility for
performance in terms of what you can do
I think most of what we're doing is sort
of prioritizing right there are times
where we want to build more powerful
features for users and there are times
where we want to go back and optimize
performance and I mean we're taking part
of this journey of making tottle an
incredibly fast platform and it's a very
fast platform today performance today is
kind of comparable to a next react setup
where actually tottle is slightly better
on the update performance so once your
application is loaded it generally
performs better than react at least for
a large complicated apps but there are
still so much more work that we can do
and and that we continuously doing on
getting that even better and even better
right you talked about the challenges to
move from staging to release and also to
have continuous deployment and how all
of that is solved in the no Cod platform
where you can immediately deploy stuff
one of the big gaps that I see in the
current existing set of nle platforms is
the lack of a test environment a staging
environment before you go into
production or deploy into production is
that something which has been solved in
total or how does that transition from a
Dev setup to production happen in total
so what we've done in total is basically
what we so often do which is look at who
do we think currently solve this the
best what is the best solution we think
is out there and then can we basically
adopt that and personally I think
platforms like versett and netlify are
the ones that has cracked this best I
for a long time haven't been a
particularly big fan of joint staging
environments where code goes to live and
eventually nobody actually knows what
they're releasing by the time they get
around to a release cycle where they
sort of netify the cell model of every
branch has its own live environment MH
and you can go and test that and verify
and do everything you want and it's is
an exact copy of what production is
going to be like or at least as much a
copy as you want you could choose to run
it against a separate server if that's
what you want to do right and so we have
the same when you create a branch in
total that branch is live from the
second you create it and every time you
change it those changes are
automatically updated so as you
developing a branch people looking at
that preview environment as they refresh
it will see the always see the latest
version of that right and so so I think
that's kind of The Best of Both Worlds
and how you then decide to manage your
deployment process again we give you
some Freedom here we strongly believe
that pushing often and early is the best
approach and using something like
feature Flags to make sure that you
control what actually gets released to
customers which is something we use
quite a lot that's our preferred way and
that's what we're sort of nudging people
towards but you still have the freedom
of doing something a little bit more
traditional saying I want this Branch to
live a little bit longer I want to do a
proper like full endend test on
everything before it releases so if I
got that correctly what you're saying is
that as an opiated platform you do not
encourage long lived staging branches
rather yes your focus is to try to get
your users to use feature Flags in
production so that specific features as
their relas can be enabled or disabled
in production yeah absolutely most of
the team I have here in totle is someone
I brought along from the last company I
was at this was the same thing we
experienced again again there that
staging environments tend to end up
being a lot more troubl than they worth
and actually there's a lot of research
there's an almost endless amount of this
ports pointing to the fact that the
ability to deploy quickly and having
quick release Cycles is the number one
thing that predicts quality of software
so we're very big proponents of that and
I think that's also what we wanted to
build with tottle we want wanted people
to get into that mindset of push early
deploy early deploy often right and of
course when you use feature flag
deploying to the main environment or to
your production environment doesn't
necessarily mean shipping new features
to customers or changes to customers you
get to do that control in your live
environment so it doesn't mean that
you're shipping things that are untested
it doesn't ship that anything is more
risky it just means you have a lot more
of a streamlined approach to software
delivery right I think you also
mentioned that most of your team are
building toddle using toddle what does
that mean well so what essentially
happened is that really early on which
is now a couple years ago of building
tottle I got to this stage where I I
started to realize that this could
actually work like okay I I might
actually be on to something because in
the early days I was sort of very
skeptical about is this even a good idea
do I even know what I'm doing right so I
ran into a lot of issues but they were
always solvable so every iteration it
seemed to work better and better and
eventually I kind of got to a point
where this seems to work like when I go
through this logically this model works
like this platform works for building
something very complicated but there's a
big difference between thinking it works
and you know theorizing that it works
and then actually knowing it works and
so I realized in order to both prove to
first of all myself but also to anyone
in the future that you can actually use
this to build very very complex
applications
I needed to build a very very complex
application and since I was a lone
person working on this that didn't make
any sense having to work on multiple
large complex systems at the same time
as a single developer and at the same
time I always knew that eventually the
ultimate test of a platform like this is
the same you see for any programm
language are you going to write the
compiler in the language itself that's
why most program languages do that today
and so I started rebuilding like I had a
version one that was built in react the
editor part right and then I started
rebuilding it in total and eventually
got to a point where I could then throw
away the react version and keep building
in total from there on interesting
moving on to the next section which is
around scalability and performance
considerations can you touch on the
strategies which have employed to ensure
that platforms can handle spikes in
traffic and usage without degradation in
performance absolutely so because we
made the choice earlier on to at least
initially and I think we don't have any
plan to expand on this but for now we're
front and only platform right right and
we do have a little bit of code running
service out we hosted on cloudflare and
we are running some code on cloudflare
workers specifically for serers side
rendering well there's two things we
handle serers side we let you proxy API
requests through a cloudflare worker and
that basically means that you don't ever
have to deal with things like cause
issues we can also handle auth ication
in a very secure way so even if you
require like an out token as part of a
header we can actually store that in an
hcp only cookie and then just add the
header on the proxy layer and thereby
making sure that your secure credentials
actually never make it to the front end
which sort of eliminates a whole Suite
of potential cross-side scripting
attacks you can do right and the other
thing is server side rendering so you
actually get like a server side rendered
version of the application as fast as
possible to the user but that's really
the only two things we do on the server
right now and since both of those hosted
on cloudflare workers they're very good
at handling spikes and traffic they're
very good at handling large scalable
things and it's all serverless so it
does scale really well so I think
scalability in terms of traffic is not a
particularly large issue for us it's
kind of almost delivered by the platform
now that's a little bit oversimplified
of course there are always challenges as
you scale but not in the sense that for
example if you providing a server as a
service solution you would have to deal
with right right got it and is that a
similar approach you take for monitoring
and analyzing the performance metrics
you know such as through Port response
times is that also something that you
rely on the cloud metric yeah so we get
a lot of it from cloud FR metric we also
use honeycomb which a distributed
tracing Analytics tool that I can highly
recommend I don't know if you've had any
of them on the podcast but it's a really
impressive tool that basically allows
you to get very detailed view of almost
down to a function running in the back
end if you want of how long did that
take to execute and what exactly took
time so when we're for example trying to
optimize page load time for total
applications we're looking at things
like how long did it take for our worker
to figure out what project it needed to
load how long did it take to fetch the
actual code or no code if you will the
actual data that needed to essentially
turn into the rendered output for that
application how long did rendering take
all these things we can break down by
each step of like what is actually the
performance and because we have that in
honeycomb we can also get like what is
the 95th percentile what is the average
all these things so we can do a lot more
detailed performance analytics of things
like how long did different pages take
to render Etc right which is a big part
of how we are also working to optimize
that performance right moving on to the
next topic which is security concerns
what are some of the common security
vulnerabilities in a no code platform
that is different from traditional
coding I don't know if they're
necessarily that different I think there
are some benefits and some setbacks if
you will I think the benefits of a no
code platform is again back to this
ideas that as you're slightly limiting
how people can do things you're also
limiting some of the bad ways that
people can do things right so one of the
things for example we're doing with
tottle is this idea of saying well you
can store your out credentials with us
and by credentials here I mean access
token I don't mean like your actual
password we never store that of course
but let's say you're logging into a
service you can sort of choose to saying
when I'm getting a token back I want to
save that as a session cookie in totle
and what we're actually doing is we're
storing it as a hcp only cookie and
thereby preventing the front end from
being able to read it again and then
whenever you're making an API request to
the service that needs it we're adding
it back in on the proxy layer and so
that sort of eliminates a whole session
like a whole Suite of potential attacks
right there and again because we can
handle a lot of it at a platform level
there's a lot of things where we can
actually make this more secure than you
wouldn't code simply because we are
closing a lot of the potential issues
right we're handling a lot of the
potential mistakes you could make as a
developer now the downside of that is
that as your advertisement platform
where everyone can learn to code it also
means everyone doesn't have experience
with software security and different
attack services so I think if you're
overall looking at NOCO today I think on
average I think it's fair to Guess that
platforms are probably a little bit less
secure than most ones written code I
don't think that's the limitation of no
code I think that is that generally on
average your no code developer is less
experienced today than most software
Engineers all right I did a quick look
up and we've not done a a specific
session on honeycomb but we did do a
session which was episode 455 where we
had Jamie r on software Telemetry and he
had discussed a range of topics or
Telemetry tools I will go and look that
up because that is probably worth it's
one of the things I only quite recently
started looking into but every now and
then you try one of these Services
Technologies where you realize you're
never ever going back right and this was
definitely one of them like having that
kind of insight into what happened in
your system once you've tried it you
never want to not have it again true are
there any specific compliance Frameworks
or certifications that organizations
should consider when using no code
platforms I don't know if there's
anything outside of mainly just your
standard service providers things you
should consider I there's a few things
that I think they're the same you should
always consider when using a service
provider so like if you're a European
company you need to be aware and
actually no better whereare your compan
is you need to be aware have things like
gdpr comply so again with totle we don't
store any data on your users if you're
using our platform so gdpr is not really
an issue in our case and also we don't
do any tracking on any app you do in
total you can obviously add that in if
you want but we are not doing that out
the buck any sort of tracking of any of
the users so that issue is not there but
if you're using a a no code backend of
course anything where you store data
these all things you need to be aware of
and of course depending on your industry
you might need to require things like
like Hipp compliance all these things y
it doesn't add any new concerns that you
don't always have if using let's say an
authentication provider or a hosted
database it's the same kind of things
you have to go the same checklist you
need to go through and verify that
actually it is well within compliance of
your requirement right moving on to the
next topic which is Enterprise adoption
what is the current state of Enterprise
adoption for no good platforms so we're
seeing really good adoption on certain
areas I mentioned earlier that no code
is this this vast space of many many
different kind of tools so when we're
looking at internal apps so for example
I think right now the key ones people
are talking a lot about rol and Jet
admin being two really popular ones they
are seeing the very positive trend also
among Enterprise customers we have one
of the earlier platforms like appgyver
which is a nood platform that was
acquired by sap so I mean that's
obviously very Enterprise focused then
right so we are seeing it we're seeing
it in specific areas and usually around
internal apps or sort of secondary apps
which means it's not used for your
primary product and again webflow also
being very successful we are seeing a
lot of really large companies and
high-profile companies building their
landing pages and web flow one area
where we haven't seen much Enterprise
adoption yet is in the actual s space
which is where tottle also is right the
area we're looking for and I think
there's largely two reasons for that one
is that the same reason I listed earlier
on as to why I built Tuttle the things
that I felt was lacking for me to be
able to commit to an existing NOCO tool
I think all those same problems is
preventing any Enterprise adoption like
you can't run an Enterprise software
team if you don't have proper Version
Control that's not really going to work
right and at the same time often when
you get to larger companies and it's
looking at their products now the larger
software teams start to talk about
things like performance budgets Etc and
it's it becomes normal for teams to
actually continuously measure
performance as you deploy and I mean
once you're getting at that level when
things like load times instead of
something you take very serious
historically a lot of the platforms just
wasn't able to deliver on that right I
think Google and Amazon both did studies
on the cost of 100 millisecond load time
and so when some platforms are saying
actually page load time is somewhere
more like five to six seconds or 3 to
six seconds right for a web shop of
Amazon scale like that would never work
it would simply not be worth it to go an
oal way and so I think for the newer
tools like tottle we simply haven't been
around long enough to get to that level
we are looking at really good adoption
from early adopters and startups getting
started with tottle and Building Things
and smaller software companies starting
to notice us and start building projects
in tottle but for these to get to
Enterprise level is going to take a lot
longer right and what's the level of
integration support provided by nood
platforms with existing it systems and
infrastructure yeah so I think that
depends a lot on the platform again
there are many different setups for if
you're looking at the kind of nood
platforms like tottle for the front end
we sort of decided early on that we
would want to start with working with
everything and then later on making
specific things easier and what I mean
by that is we started out building a
really good system for connecting to hcp
and rest apis right
so basically no matter what your API is
and where it's hosted and what platform
it is it's really easy to connect to it
because everything speaks HTP and then
later on we're beginning to look at how
can we make this even easier for a
select amount of platforms so actually
build easy to use Integrations on top of
the substraction but by default you can
connect to anything so there's nothing
you can't integrate with just like when
you're building your front end react
you're using fetch to connect to your
backend right so it works with
everything you don't have an integration
that you need to look at right for some
of the other tools I think one of the
tools that I discovered fairly early on
is a tool called make there's actually
two really big competing tools in the
same category Sapia and make and they're
basically like a sort of glue code or
glue no code if you will for services
and what they basically do is you can
sort of set up Integrations to call each
other and then add a little bit of logic
in way so you can do like when I get
this stripe web web Hook when this
stripe web Hook is called actually call
this workflow that I set up in let's say
Sapia and then from that call let's
insert a road into my database or call a
hook in mailer light to send an email to
someone so you can build all these
automation workflows really efficiently
and both of these platform has like
thousands of Integrations so depending
on where you are some of them are really
really well integrated and designed for
that and some of them are a lot more
flexible and sort of has you do a little
bit more yourself but sort of allow you
to still work with pretty much any
platform you're looking to agreed I make
sure we'll link to those tools in our
show nodes but make is quite an easy one
to remember it's make.com and very
flexible yeah absolutely we actually
it's one of the tools we also use as
part of our stack so we obviously build
the front end in total and then we're
using cloudflare workers as sort of a
proxy layer for servers side rening on
apis but we also have super base which
is sort of I think generally considered
more of a low code or just a a backend
as a service platform as well as make as
sort of being a glue that binds a lot of
different services and workflows
together what's the role of it
departments and governance teams in
supporting and overseeing the adoption
of new good Platforms in an Enterprise
oh that's a good question it
Department's role would probably change
a bit but I suppose it's largely the
same trend we've seen with devops
happening over the last couple of years
as you're managing a lot less of your
own software and a lot more get hosted
these roles start to change and so in
that sense no code are largely manager
service manag the platform that takes
care of a lot of the management of your
infrastructure so you don't have to do
it yourself so in a lot of ways it's
just kind of a continuation of that same
Trend I think governance and compliance
those things doesn't necessarily really
change too much their roles as they see
today I think you always need to
validate your suppliers and in this case
your NOCO platform is another supplier
right so it's as this becomes part of
your service infrastructure it's part of
the network of services that you need to
be aware of and understand what data is
available there what are we actually
providing them what are the agreements
we have for them how do you see the
landscape of Enterprise adoption of new
good platforms evolving in the future
and what trends or developments do you
anticipate emerging I think the trend
we're on now the trajectory on right now
where we're seeing certain types of tool
being adopted very quickly I think a lot
of the build internal tools is sort of
the easiest to adopt because I think
it's the one that carries largely the
less risk it's not being exposed to your
customers and it's not also usually not
a critical part of a data flow Etc right
but we're also beginning to see these
tools like sapier and make making the
way to Enterprise and actually being
adopted by really large customers that
are running very large workflows through
these no code systems and I think we're
generally seeing which often happens in
Enterprise it tends to not be the
quickest early adapters but we're seeing
sort of a continuing move forward of
adopting more and more of these types of
software because I think for most of
them they see the values there right the
easier it is to automate something the
easier it is to set up and build
essentially the easier it is to manage
for last Enterprise as well so we're
seeing kind of a steady Trend towards
more and more adoption of these services
and I think that'll continue I
absolutely believe that we'll start
seeing the first Enterprise companies
whose entire products are built on a no
code stack and if not maybe entire then
at least the majority of the stack will
be built in in a no code solution
interesting times we've covered a lot of
ground over there and as we wrap up a
couple of questions was there anything
we missed that you'd like to mention no
I don't I think we've covered it pretty
well I think I obviously want to say
that for anyone out there that is
interested in trying tottle it's
completely free to sign up and you can
also deploy your software and share it
with anyone anything you build in tottle
without having to go on a pay plan so I
would encourage everyone to go and try
that and see how far this world of no
code has actually come especially if we
have some older more seasoned Engineers
there that's tried some of the early ear
generation visual programming languages
out there if people want to find out
more about what you're up to where can
they go yeah so definitely check out
totle dodev to o d dle dodev our website
and that's where you can also go and
sign up we are also very active on
Twitter at totev and I would also
recommend checking out our YouTube
channel we got a lot of content on how
to start building with totle we
especially have a playlist in a course
called first week in total so if you're
just starting out and have no idea how
it works that's a really good place to
sort of start learning how to use this
tool thank you Andreas for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure this is
bries for software engineering radio
thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
SE-R to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening